uh okay there's a number of topics i want to talk about today uh this is our
last lecture and i want to keep some time at the end for
like you know random questions on random topics that you might want to ask
you know maybe sort of general questions in general about like approaches to
machine learning ai deep learning etc uh you know maybe questions really
you know kind of you know maybe that may be a little more philosophical but
um but let me start with uh something more concrete so
um i want to talk about structure prediction i alluded to this topic a
number of times during the previous lectures but i think not enough
in depth for for most people to understand so i want
to come back to this so structure prediction is basically
the problem of uh predicting a variable that itself is not just like a single
category or uh you know a single object but
basically a sort of a combinatorial object so for for
example things like a sentence you're doing speech recognition you're
doing handwriting recognition you're doing natural language
generation or translation and what you need to output is a sort of
grammatically correct consistent sequence of symbols
and there is no you can't say that there is a
a finite number of possibilities of the output because the
the length of the output might be variable uh but even if it's
if the length is has a maximum and the number is in principle finite
because it's combinatorial um there's no way to kind of enumerate all possible
different outputs and so to express the the type constraint that the output has
to reflect that's that's what's called structural prediction and
this uh you know there's a lot of work on this
going back uh uh to basically the early days of speech
recognition so this is not a recent problem
um and in fact the the i'm going to start by a little bit of history uh in
my mind the the first model to do structural
prediction combined with things like neural
networks uh trained discriminatively was this speech recognition model for uh
four words by uh javier de la cruz ii back in the
early 90s 1991 and there was kind of similar work about
the same time by joshua banjo and about a year or two later by patrick hefner
so these are people who worked on discriminative training
for systems are supposed to produce a sequence of symbols
uh from uh uh you know a signal that says speech
or handwriting and where once the the first step basically
is a neural net uh here uh in this this neural net i wrote td
and n this means time data neural net is basically a temporal convolutional net
uh so this is the you know the first model i i can
i can find of uh structural prediction uh sort of
hybridized with with neural nets if you want
so the problem that uh the idler currently ubuntu are trying to solve was
recognizing words using a neural net and to some extent the modern approaches
are kind of similar to this but in in some ways
so the speech signal is represented as a sequence of acoustic vectors
so those are uh you know you you you slice the signal into
little chunks and then on one of the chunks you do a for your transform which
uh fredo has explained to you and you turn
it into basically a feature vector and you have one of those vectors
it's typically 30 dimensions or so maybe 40.
and you want one of those vectors every 10 milliseconds so
so about 100 times per second so you have a sequence of 40 dimensional
vectors uh uh about 100 per second and you you
you run this through a convolutional net a temporal convolutional net and at the
output of it uh what you get is a sequence of feature
vectors you can think of it this way uh in modern systems those feature
vectors are actually uh kind of soft max factors that indicate a
category but in that case it wasn't um and those can be at the same
rate or they can be slower so if the if the neural net has
if the conversion that has temporal sep sampling you're not going to get
10 of those feature vectors per second you might get you know 25
um you know two and a half or something right oh i'm sorry
at the input there is a hundred so if you have a sub sampling by a factor of
four you will get 25 feature vectors per
second not 100. or something like that now here's the
problem the problem is you want to recognize which word was just pronounced
and different people will pronounce the same word at different speeds and so
what you need to do is uh what's called dynamic time wiping
and i explained this uh already in the in the past
so let's imagine that you've recorded this person you don't want to do
uh speaker independent speech recognition for now just speaker
specific so you've recorded that person saying uh uh you know let's say the
the ten digits uh uh spoken digits like zero one two three four five etc
because you're only interested in recognizing uh
uh spoken digits isolated spoken digits maybe this is
a system that is supposed to uh you know dial
a number uh on your phone right so it just needs to recognize sequences of
digits or perhaps it's a very simple speech
recognition system that tries to spot the the wake up word for uh you know
amazon alexa or something like this so the only thing the system is supposed
to recognize is alexa or hey google or you know something like that right a
wake up word um so uh the system may have a bunch of
uh pre-recorded templates that correspond to uh
sequences of future vectors uh that were produced by uh someone
speaking each of the words um and now the way you want to train the
system is that you would like to train the neural net at the same time as
the template so that the overall system recognizes the words uh as best as
possible this is a classification problem
but there is a latent variable in it and the latent variable is how
how are you going to time warp the sequence of future vectors so that it
matches the length of those templates and again i'm kind of
repeating myself because i talked a little bit about this before
so you do this with damage time wiping and what that consists of
is that you line up all the feature vectors
along the bottom here of this so this is think of this as a matrix
you line up all the future vectors uh at the uh at the input so that you get the
the sequence of future vectors are here and then you put the sequence of
template vectors so uh future vectors coming out of the
template on this axis and then each entry in the matrix
is an indication of the distance between the feature vector
here and the feature vector there okay so you get this probability matrix with
uh distances between feature vectors essentially
um and the best uh the best way to map the sequence of each vector into another
one to to see if they fit is to basically view this matrix as kind
of a a set of nodes in a graph and what you
want is go from the lower left hand corner of that graph to
the upper right hand corner by going through a path that
minimizes the sum of the distances along the past
okay uh so obviously you're going to have to go
horizontally you know more steps than you go vertically so
on a few occasions you're going to diagonally in a few occasions you're
going to go vertically up but on many occasions you're probably going to go
horizontally to the to the right and that would be
the situation where you have multiple feature vectors here
that are essentially identical that match
the single feature vector in the template okay so for example
you pronounce the word seven very slowly the uh
uh initially it's gonna be you know repeated multiple times because you you
stick on it for like a quarter of a second so
you're gonna have 25 instances of this and all of this will be mapped to
maybe a single feature actor here that corresponds to this
sound up um so finding this path that best warps the
the the sequence into the template sequence
is like minimizing with respect to a related variable z okay
so it's like you have an energy function and you're minimizing this energy
function with respect to the relative variable
the latent variable is the path in that graph um so now what you have is
the best warping that matches the sequence of future vector to the first
template now you keep doing it with doing the
with with doing this with all the templates
okay so for every template every word you know from zero
one two three to nine you have the best way to warp
the the the feature vector to that template
um and uh and now you can if your system has been trained you you
pick the the category of the word template
with a smaller distance okay as simple as that that's for
classification now how about training so for training
um this is a latent variable model essentially and what you need to do
is you need to make the energy for the correct answer as small
as possible and make sure the energy for the
incorrect answers are larger okay so um so let's imagine the correct
answer is is oops sorry
is this word here the second last one that correspond to zero one two three
the category three for example okay so we know the correct answer is
three so what we need to do now is uh basically change the word template
here a little bit so that it gets closer to the the feature vector sequence
and then change the feature vector sequence so that it gets closer to the
template right you can think of this dtw uh
distance this dynamic time warping distance as a kind of distance
uh which involves minimization with respect to a path but in the end it's
some sort of distance or divergence and what you need to do is and that's
basically your energy so what you need to do is make that distance smaller
for the correct answer okay so the energy of the correct answer goes down
uh and simultaneously you need to make sure the energy of all the e correct
answers get uh are larger okay so you might need to
push them away so you might need to have an objective
function that is going to uh take the templates for the wrong
words and somehow push them away from the current sequence of features
okay so that's how you learn the templates
um and then simultaneously uh you you need to you you're gonna have kind
of a combination of gradients that are gonna back propagate through this dtw
one um one is going to try to make that a
sequence of feature vector uh such that once you go the time wiping
it gets closer to the correct word template but also uh
change it so that it gets away from the the other templates the the templates
for the other categories okay um so that is simply
back propagating through the uh you know through the dynamic time marking and the
dynamic time marking really is a switch it's a giant switch right
it basically tells you uh those values here
on the along the path matter because uh they are the ones that indicate whether
my input vector matches my template vector okay
all the other ones that my pass is is not taking are irrelevant they don't
matter so the distance is just the sum of those
values so when i back propagate i just get
uh for each vector here a gradient that corresponds to
uh the gradient of uh you know basically the
the distance uh to the corresponding vector in the template
so for the correct template this is going to cause
all those vectors to get closer to the corresponding vector in the template
and all those vectors to move away from the corresponding vector in the
bad templates that you decide to push away and then you can just back prop and
get those gradients all the way through now i'm kind of explaining the mechanics
of it but you don't actually have to think
about it you know in principle kind of um
conceptually it's just a energy-based model with lithium variable
and you just compute the gradient of your energy with respect to
uh you know to everything in your in your network
uh for you know values related variables that depend on
you know the position of the of uh of this switch here you can think of this
switch as the one that tells you which of the answers is correct
and so it's nothing more than an energy-based model
okay now there's a question um so why am i introducing this before talking
about structure prediction because this is a very simple
form of structure prediction particularly if now the problem is not
to recognize a single word but it is to recognize a sequence of
words right so a word is a sequence of sounds uh but a
sentence is a sequence of words and so therefore also a sequence of
sounds right so i could build uh a collection of possible
sequences which are grammatically correct
sequences of words which correspond to some grammatically correct sequences of
sounds and then this kind of dynamic time
marking if you want will sort of find among all the possible uh sequences of
uh of symbols or or or sounds or words
we'll find the one that has the lowest energy
okay that this future vector is closest to somehow
okay so that's the general problem with sequence labeling
and um and it can be formulated uh
at a general level uh in this way um now i'm i'm kind of uh i kind of set the
stage a little bit and now i'm going to talk about something that you're not
going to see immediately is connected but um it's gonna come up at the end
okay so let's say you have a learning system
that is uh composed of an input x okay it gets an input x
and it's an energy model in which the energy is a sum of three terms in this
case so those those uh blue squares here are basically
factors in a factor graphs they're energy terms
additive energy terms in your energy function
uh and your output is uh is a sequence in this case a sequence of four symbols
and those symbols um do not all uh contribute to all the terms in the
energy so basically your energy function the first term
takes into account the first two output [Music]
symbols or or variables in your in your output in your sequence of output
the second one take the second two the third one takes the
the third and fourth okay now imagine that
um this were a sequence of words and your system was supposed to do
something like speech recognition or something so x is the speech signal
uh in the blue boxes you have neural nets and various other things there
might be another neural net that looks at x
x and then produces future vectors that go into those boxes but
uh that's the detail for now um and um what those blue boxes would would
have to uh implement is basically grammatical
constraints so uh you know in english certain words can
follow others but not uh others right so you rarely have two
two verbs that follow each other um and so you could implement this in
this uh energy term that would make you pay a
price for uh you know making a verb follow another
verb all right or having uh i don't know you know two
prepositions you can have two objectives that follow each other
you know things like that right so basically those would you know implement
sort of basic grammatical rules and you can think of this as kind of a
language model right so i know what word came before
uh tell me what work and can come after and i can train this on the corpus of
text to learn this energy function so
you know it's a it would be a very basic crude language model
so this type of model would implement a very cool language model
by just you know taking the previous word and then telling you what the the
next word what next words are possible making you
pay a price for picking a word that is not
uh not correct um okay so um how you do inference this is
just a basically an energy model here which in
this case doesn't actually have a lithium variable but
basically i give you an x and you have to find the sequence of y that minimizes
the energy but in this case because the energy is
the sum of three terms the efficient way to find the sequence
of y's that minimize the energy that may not require
a completely exhaustive search or gradient descent or something like this
okay i'm going to place myself in a situation where why
the y's are actually discrete okay so this thing's like words or
or sounds or categories of some kind and so this applies to uh
you know this situation where the the variables you need to infer are all
outputs which means they're going to be visible
on the training set and you can train your system to kind of infer them
correctly but it could also be another situation where
uh you know some of the variables are observed like x here on the left
and y is observed during training on the right but then all the intermediate
variables are never observed there are latent variables they need to you need
to minimize over um as well but again here this factor
graph is factorized in the sense that the energy is a sum of of different
terms that only take subsets of the variables into
account all right okay so let's say uh let's
take a very concrete example now and let's say the uh
energy here in this case is a sum of four terms
four energy terms okay uh the first two uh depend on x
the observation the last one depend uh the last two depend on y which is the
variable you need to predict which you're given during training but not
during tests and then two other nodes are our latent
variable nodes okay and let's say uh x is some high
dimensional variable we don't care what it is because we just observe it
and z1 is binary z2 is binary y1 is binary and y2 is ternary so we can
take three values zero one two okay now uh
if you count how many possible configurations of z one z two y one y
two they are there are basically uh
uh uh 24 right uh two times two times two times three right
that's that's 24 uh different possible configurations of
values so if you wanted to do exact inference uh you might have to try
all 24 of those configurations and then compute the energy of all 24 of
those configurations and then pick the one with the lowest energy
to do inference right and in fact those those 24 configurations correspond to
uh 24 times three evaluations of those energy terms right because we
have three energy terms so we'll have to compute 96 different
energies to be able to do this okay and this is a small example where
the sequence is short and the the the variables are binary okay this
goes exponentially with the number of with the length of
the sequence uh and uh uh
uh sorry with the the number of uh possible values of the of the
of the z's uh and the length of the sequence so if you have
you know uh uh you know n possibilities for each of the
variables and the length is l you know it's n to the l right exponential in the
ninth okay but the thing is there is a more
efficient way of figuring out what is the configuration of lowest
energy and it's due to the fact that you have
those kind of local this local structure right so uh z1 can only take two values
okay and z2 can only also only take two values
so this energy term here can only take four values it's ever going to see
only four different values because it can only see
zero zero zero one one zero one one right
so you could imagine could be pre-computing those four values
okay this guy is also going to see only four values right so you can
you can because this is binary and that binary that's binary
so you can pre-compute those four values okay
so that's another four evaluation of an objective function that we're up to
eight and this guy has six different values
because this variable is binary this one ternary so it's
two by two times three so now you have six different configurations
so by pre-computing the four here the four here and the six here
um uh you you have computed all the possible uh configurations basically
and that's kind of represented here at the bottom so
this is called a trellis and it's basically a graph that has a source node
and a target node and every path in a graph corresponds to
a particular assignment of of the variables okay
so for example if i go through this path okay it means y1 equals z1 equals 1
z2 equals 0 y1 equals 1 and y2 equals 2 let's say okay
and if i add up the the terms on each arc i get the overall energy
each arc is is uh basically annotated by the
energy term the value of the energy that corresponds to this configuration
so for example this arc here is this energy and that's the value of this
energy term for y one equals one and y two equals two
okay uh so each of these args is a value of
this energy term each of these rx is the value of that energy term
etc and now the finding the the best lowest energy
configuration of z1 z2 y1 y2 simply consists in
finding the shortest path in this graph okay and
to do this i only have to evaluate uh four times four terms of energy here
four terms here and six terms here and that's
it okay so that's uh 14 i don't know why i said 16 here or 16
because of the first two here yes so 16 values total
but uh so that's a lot less than 96 okay and that's because
the energy is the sum of terms and you can use those kind of efficient
algorithms uh to do the inference okay so this is a
simple case where the output is a sequence
and when the output is a sequence there is a simple algorithm
and it's basically shoulder space in a graph right in a in a trellis
so that's just dynamic programming uh um and it's very simple it's efficient you
know it's uh it's nice so to train a system like this
what you need to tell it is you need to tell it here is the correct
configuration of y1 y2 i don't know what z1z2 is because it's a latent variable
so find me the path that goes to the correct
uh combination of y1 y2 okay so you know that let's say y1 equal
1 and y2 equal 2. so you know that the correct path
has to include this link right and so there's only a subset of
path for the the previous ones that are
possible right you can't go to y one equals zero because
that would be incorrect uh so basically only this this guy survives
and then the other paths you can take whatever you want as long as you get to
that point so you can just find the one that minimizes the energy here
so minimizing energy with respect to z1 z2 so that
uh y1 and y2 take the right value okay constraining where when
where you to take the the right value and the way you train the system now is
that you migrate and descent you back you back propagate the gradient of the
overall energy okay for this particular y and this
particular x and the z that you obtain by minimizing
you back propagate uh the the the gradient of of this energy with
respect to the parameters of all those energy terms
and you try to make that smaller right you know you have the correct y the
correct x and whatever z value uh
z mistake try to make that energy lower by tweaking the parameters
at the same time uh you have to make sure the energy of incorrect answers for
y1 and y2 that are incorrect is higher right so you take other values
of y1 y2 uh including y1 equals zero and y2
equals whatever it wants okay and for all of those other
configurations of y1y2 you want to make sure whatever energy
you you get by minimizing over z is higher than whatever you got for the
correct one okay so your loss function is going to
be something where you take the energy of the correct
answer you try to make it lower and then you take the energies of incorrect
answers and you try to make them larger okay that's discriminative
uh training for structure prediction structural prediction because the
structure here is uh represented by this uh
you know sequence of of costs okay but conceptually at a high level it's no
different from everything we talked about before when
we have a latin variable and when we train with a criterion that
says i want to make the energy of the correct time so small and the energy of
all the other answers higher okay any question at this point um i had a
question so based on this diagram it seems like
this this network only really takes discrete
values um and my understanding was that
back propagation doesn't isn't really effective if you
just have only working with discrete values
so i'm wondering if i'm missing something or if that's like
how how you connect those things right okay so uh in this case z1 z2 y1
y2 are not variables that that you learn okay they're labels
essentially okay they're discrete so one way to are
discrete just like uh you know the the class the category at
the output of the continent is discrete except you have two of them but whatever
z1 z2 are basically of the same nature the discrete variables
they're not things you're going to learn by grading descent they're just latent
variable you you have to to minimize over to do inference right
let's not talk about learning for now once your system is trained right i give
you an x and by energy minimization you find z1 z2 y1 y2
that minimizes the energy okay and because you've trained the
correct y1y2 to have the lowest energy among all
possible configurations of y2 you're going to get the correct one okay
now uh for training the the training takes
place uh you know uh basically affects the
parameters of each of those factors inside those factors there are
parameters you know w a w b w c w d which i i didn't
represent here and the way you train the system is you
you say you know at the gradient of the energy of the correct answer
uh with respect to those parameters i'm going to tweak the parameters so that
energy goes down that's continuous uh differentiable
okay and then simultaneously i have the energy of bad answers
i'm going to back propagate gradients and according to my loss function i'm
going to push up the energy of those so that my energy my loss function goes
down okay my training objective goes down
not my energy right now so so now the what i'm explaining it
down there with the trellis is the fact that because those variables
are discrete you can't use gradient descent to infer
them okay and so you have to infer them by
combinatorial search essentially and the first solution i i mentioned with
the 96 factor evaluations uh basically is exhaustive search right
try every combination of z one z two y one y two
and we and figure out which one has the lowest energy
but uh but the whole point of this is that this is wasteful
in the sense that because the energy decomposes into terms that only take
subsets of variables you can actually decompose this into uh
you can reduce this to finding the shortest paths in a graph
where the transitions in this graph are are annotated by the energies that
correspond to the value of the variables of the two
corresponding nodes okay now this is a slightly more general
form of what i told you about earlier uh so this this model here
with the dynamic time marking uh is very much the same right you you
you know the z1 z2 here are basically the paths in the dynamic time marking
uh module the y is which of the word template matches
okay and the training consists in just you
know doing gradient descent to make the energy
of the correct answer small and the energy of the incorrect answer is larger
using some loss function which i lift i live unspecified at the moment
professor when you say that you're finding that the shortest um the
shortest path you're saying that the distance between
nodes is the energy between the nodes uh the the shortest path is the path
that has the smallest sum of terms along along the along the edges right so
each edge here is marked by an energy so for
example this edge here is marked by the energy
of the term uh b uh when z one equals zero
and z two equals one okay okay so if i take this path i'm gonna
pay that energy right and if i take this this
edge i'm going to pay that energy and so you know finding the lowest energy
configuration of variables consisting finding the path
with the the the smallest sum of uh value along on the edges along that
path okay so it's the shortest path in the
graph okay is that clear
yeah that makes sense thank you and then so the the zeros before the
the black node those are zeros just because the the summation itself is zero
energy right is that is that yeah that's right yeah
okay no i'm not counting uh yeah like i don't care which of those
paths it is right i don't have an energy term here for uh
like what's the value of y2 so if i had an extra factor here
that only took y2 then uh that factor would basically put an
energy here on the you know we replace those zeros
right okay there's a question here coming from
the students so we are pushing down on the energy or
we are actually doing a minimization for training and inference but then when
are we actually pushing up just during training all right so let me
remind you how uh training energy-based models work
right particularly contrasting methods uh and if you have latent variables
right so you have your you have your energy function e of xyz
uh sorry the arguments are in the wrong order here it
doesn't matter so you have your energy function e of xyz
i give you i give you an x so in in training mode i give you an x and a y
i don't give you z ever but i give you an x and a y here is a
training sample it's an x and a y the first thing you do is you find a z
that minimizes the the energy e of x y z okay and you call that f of x y
right but the way you compute it is just min over z of e of x y z
now uh for for the the correct y in your training
set you want that energy to be small right and for your inference algorithm
to work at test time at this time i don't give
you the y i just give you the x and what you have to find is the y that
has the smallest energy so for this to work
it has to be the case that the correct y has the lowest energy among all possible
y's right so what i need to do now during
training is that i give you the correct y and
what you need to do is give a low energy to the correct y
and give a higher energy to every other possible configuration of y
right and exactly how you do this or how
all those energies enter in your objective function
uh depends on the objectives that you choose we're going to come to this in a
minute okay but almost certainly you're going
to have one term in your last function that's going to say make the energy of
the correct answer low and another term that that's going
to say make the energy of all the other answers or some of them
high and we talked about this last time actually three weeks ago okay but i'm
going to come back to it right is that clear or do you need
another clarification uh i don't see any reply
here okay
all right um another one would be what if the
factor graph is not possible do we have to search for all possible combination
of ys maybe i think this is the continuous
case i think no not necessarily so uh i mean
this this idea of decomposing into uh energies also gives you an advantage
even in the case of continuous variables right because you can do independent
optimizations like like the combination of uh values
of z1 and z2 uh only affects eb you know even if z1
and z2 are continuous and so you can do kind of the a little
bit of the equivalent of dynamic programming there it's a little
more complicated in the continuous case but
uh but it could be uh uh possible yeah i mean the the worst situation
is when uh all the z's and the y's enter a giant factor and there is no way
of factorizing it and then you know you
have to do exhaustive search or some approximate uh search heuristics
okay inference algorithm that minimizes the energy
yeah yeah that was actually the case the student was referring it
and the other student is also satisfied so you answer both questions
yeah don't hesitate to ask if you do something that's not clear
okay so uh here is a an instance of this uh and if you encounter this in uh the
literature you'll know what it is it's called a
conditional random field okay so conditional random field
is a very special type of such uh structural prediction model
where uh you know the here you have y's or these doesn't matter
here they're only wise but the the way those factors are parameterized
is that there is a fixed feature extractor let's call it f of x y
one y two in this case here uh and then a weight vector that just
computes the dot product of this future vector uh with with this
weight vector and that gives you a score here
uh just an energy okay the overall energy is just the sum of all those
terms so basically those are shadow neural nets if you want
single layer neural nets with a feature extractor at the input
and then we can think about like what type of uh loss function are we going to
minimize to train something like this so one possibility is to use the
negative likelihood loss so basically you say i
want the energy of the correct answer to be
low and i want the log of the sum of the exponentials of all
the energies of all the bad all the answers including
the good one uh uh to be uh
to be large okay uh in fact more more more correctly you
want the minus log of the sum of
all configurations of your output of the exponential minus
the energy of all those configurations to be as small as possible
okay um so um so basically you want the the
combination of energies or bad answers to be as large as possible
okay and we've encountered that loss function before
right i mean that's basically what's using softmax softmax says that softmax
says uh i want the the you know
negative log probability of the correct answer to be as low as possible the
probability of the correct answer to be as
large as possible that's like an energy okay
but then simultaneously i compute the the sum of the exponential the log of
the sum of the exponentials of all the answers
okay and i want that to be uh to be small i want all those energies to
be uh to be large i want all those probabilities to be
small okay soft max does that to you when you
or logs of max criterion when you back propagate it it does
classification and it does exactly that it pushes
down the energy of the correct answer it pushes out the energies of all the other
answers by computing the log of the sum of the
answers of exponential minus the energies
um so here uh conditional random field is basically an example of that but
you're not doing classification you're doing kind of structured prediction
and uh in the positive case you have the correct
uh configuration of y one y two y four one one way two or three and four and
the incorrect ones are not you know uh incorrect categories as in
uh as in classification but there are
incorrect configurations of y1 y2 or 3y4 other than that it's just you know
backprop i mean it's not even backward here because it's a shallow network
if you put a whole neural net in there parametrized by w's that
would be perfectly kosher and uh that would be kind of a deep conditional
random field if you want which happened to actually exist before conditional
running fields uh here's another idea you can use a
hinge loss so the hinge last says i want the energy of the correct answer
to be low and then among all possible configurations of incorrect answers
incorrect configurations of ys i'm going to look for the one that has the lowest
energy among all the wrong all the bad ones and
that one i'm going to push up okay i don't need to push the other ones
because they are larger anyway so i'm just going to you know figure out
which configuration of y1y2 by 3y4 is both incorrect but among all
incorrect configurations has the lowest energy and then push that
up okay and the way i push up and push down
is i'm going to put the difference of those two energies in a hinge loss
so that the hinge will push the energy of the correct answer to be low
and will push the energy of the incorrect
most offending answer to be higher by at least some margin
okay um so that's called the maximum margin uh
mark of net if you regularize the weights with least square and if you
have this kind of linear parametrization of
the energy terms you can also use the perception loss and
michael collins who's a well-known professor at colombia in nlp
actually you know kind of made a success you know built his career around this
idea of using perception lots for structural
prediction so that perception loss only works if you have linear parametrization
of the factors if you make them deep neural nets you can't use the perception
loss anymore it's because the margin is zero we
talked about this a little bit before but i'll come back to it in a minute
um right so uh so those ideas have been
around for a long time the probably the first people to
to think about things like this where people who worked on what's called
discriminative training for speech recognition and that goes back to the
late 80s early 90s so yo-yo and rabinera for example at
atnt had something they called minimum
empirical error loss and this is kind of a particular loss for a speech
recognition system they didn't have neural nets they had
some other way of kind of turning uh speech signals into you know
basically sound categories if you want um but but they had this way of training
at the sequence level uh by not telling the system you know
here is this sound at that location that's on that location
we're just telling it uh here is uh an input
uh sentence here is the transcription of it in terms of words
you know figure it out by doing this time warping um
you know in the context of hidden markov models which is kind of very similar
to to the the damage mapping i was talking you talking about earlier
then as i said in the early 90s people started working on
using neural nets to kind of feed one of those kind of
uh structural prediction system as i said the first one i know about is by
xavier de la cruz number two for speech recognition
but they had a 10 delay neural that joshua benjo did his phd on this
um and and had some results around 1992 and patrick hafner the the year after
that um uh leonbotul joshua benjamin patrick
hefner are the co-authors of uh my paper from 1998 about handwriting
recognition because i hired all three of them at a t
to work on this problem that figure basically figured out
you know somewhere doing this in the phd thesis and i i knew that was
the the trick uh that needed to be worked on for
things like handwriting recognition structural prediction with neural nets
um right uh let's see
okay so um so here is a way um and i only alluded to this really
quickly in an earlier lecture here's a way to sort of
put this in the context of deep learning so as i said before one
way to to do this in the context of deep learning
is you make those factors deep neural nets basically right they
just compute some energy and they are parameterized by a bunch of
parameters and nothing changes uh you you know we know how to do back
prop and we have pi torch um but here is uh uh here's a slightly
different idea and this which kind of draws on the same type of
of model and this is when uh the
the structure is more complex than just you know a bunch of fixed factors
from uh known um with a known structure if you want
so the example i'm going to use here is uh is handwriting recognition but
you know because there's a long history of it and i have uh
uh you know drawings that are that are prepared for this
that have been around for a long time but okay so
um so here the problem we have is that you know we have a sequence of
digits at the input and we don't know how to
uh segment this digit into individual this this sequence into individual
digits because we don't know what the parts are for each of the digits
the four here is kind of broken into two parts
and so what we can do is uh build a graph in which each path
is a possible way of breaking up this sequence of uh blobs into
into characters right so i can group you know i can make each of the separate
pieces a separate character so that's the path at the top i can
group the first two pieces three four and the left part of the four
and then have the last two be separate or i can have the first uh the first um
uh be by itself the the following two be regrouped and then
the last one be by itself right so what have i done here i've
basically uh uh said okay
the way i do i did inference in the in the context of soccer prediction
was by having uh uh energy terms that tell me the the the
the cost of a particular combination of variables
right so this this graph here represents basically
is a explicit representation of that energy model uh as long as i put on
those arcs here the energies that are computed by those by those modules
for each each value but what if i just manipulate this this
graph so what if uh you know the state
that i manipulate in a neural net is not a particular assignment or
variable together with something to compute energies but it's
directly a graph like this okay so a graph like this basically you
can think of as representing a list of energies for every possible
configurations of the of the variables of interest
okay it's a compact way of representing uh a list of energies for all
configurations of the sequences of symbols um
so what if i i build a neural net so that this internal states of that
neural net are basically those uh those graphs
and the graphs are just again i repeat a compact way of representing a list of
energies for every possible configurations of the variable of
interest nothing more okay
so uh but i can use this for other things and energies
so here a path in a graph corresponds to a particular way of breaking up
this uh blobs of ink into into characters and each path is a
particular way of grouping those blobs into into characters i can run
those uh images so now this graph is annotated
by images not by energies okay uh i can run those images through a
comment the content is going to tell me for each arcs in this graph is
going to tell me well this is very likely to be a three and
here is the energy for that three okay low energy if it's a good three
high energy if it's a bad three um it could also tell me well this may
be a two but uh with a higher energy or it could be a
zero with a higher energy okay so it's going to build this graph which
you can uh which you can call the uh interpretation
graph each path in this graph is a possible labeling
of each path in this graph and the labels you know indicate the categories
and the energies attached to the to the arcs
are basically the energies of the you know produced by
my comp net here for each of those answers okay
so uh discount net is going to look at this little piece of a four
it's going to tell me well that looks kind of like a two with a low energy or
that may look like a piece of a four with a higher energy
okay uh the guy that looks at this piece who's you know it's somewhere here is
going to tell me well this is a four i'm quite sure of it
uh with low energy and you know it's going to tell me maybe it's something
else with higher energy so each of those arcs here is going to
be replaced by 10 arcs i'm only representing two here but
uh essentially 10 arcs corresponding to the 10 possible categories
each of them with a different energy that is just the output
of the corresponding output of the continent that are applied here
now inference again is finding the shortest path in this graph
so uh you know finding the path with the minimum energy basically right
so finding the shortest path so it's basically
you can think of it as a module that selects uh
that you know selects the shortest path in fact it's this one here i call the
future transformer so the the word transformer
in the context of neural nets was used in 1997 but it's been you know
kind of recycled for something else now
right okay so here's a complete example of how this might work
um so again we have an input an input image
we run this through this kind of segmenter that proposes
multiple alternative segmentations which are ways to group those
blob of links together each fact in the in this graph corresponds to one
particular way of grouping the the blobs of ink we run each of those
through a neural net uh identical copies of the same content
that just is trying to do character recognition okay
each of those comp nets produces a list of 10 scores so it tells
you know this guy tells me this is one with energy 0.1 this is 4 with energy
2.4 etc this guy tells me well this piece is
four with energy point six or nine with energy 1.2 or whatever etc etc
right uh this guy is going to give me kind of relatively high energy for
everything because that doesn't look good
same for this guy okay so now i get a graph here and think of it as kind of
a weird form of tensor right it's a sparse tensor really
okay it's something that says uh it's a tensor that you know for each
possible configuration of this variable tells me the the cost of that of that
variable so it's not really it's more like a
distribution over tensors if you want okay or log distribution it's not
normalized because we're talking about energies
um okay then i take this this graph and i uh
i want to compute the energy of the correct answer because i'm you know i
might want to train the system right so i'm telling you the correct answer is
three four select within those paths the one that
actually says three four okay and there's two of them there's
three four with energy uh point one plus point six
and then there is three four with energy 3.4 plus 2.4
which is my trial right so i get those two paths
and then among those two paths i i pick the best one
uh three four okay so i told the system here is the correct answer give me the
path that has the lowest energy but yet gives me the correct answer
okay so finding that path is like minimizing over a latent variable where
the latent variable is which path you pick
right because actually it's an energy model where the latent variable is a
path a professor yes three or four in the
graph should be labeled before training or that that latent variable will figure
out for the system uh so here uh
i'm putting myself in a situation where i'm gonna train the system supervised i
know the correct answer this is the desired answer
think of this as a target okay so we just know the
target but i don't know which part is three and which part is for
well that's right so we know what the target is we don't know which path has
the correct uh is the correct segmentation right it
could be it could be this path or it could be
that path right and and here what we do is we just
pick the the one with the lowest energy which happened to be the correct one
here okay so is this recognition transformer
is each of these like um you know n and box are each are those all shared
like okay yeah this is multiple copies of the same neural net
right it's just a character recognition in this case
um okay now you have we have the energy of the correct answer
it's 0.7 it's the sum of 0.1 and 0.6 okay and what we need to do now is back
propagate gradient through this entire structure
so that we can change the weights of that neural net in such a way that this
energy goes down okay and this looks daunting but it's
entirely possible because this entire system here is built
out of uh elements that we already know about
that's just a regular neural net and those passed electrons and v2
transformers are basically switches that pick
uh you know a particular edge or not right so it's like a switch
it's like max pooling it's except it's min pulling if you want
okay right so how do i propagate well this point seven is just the sum of
this point one and this point six so uh if i have uh if i compute the
gradient of this with respect to this point one it's it's
just one the gradient of of this output with
respect to this value here 0.6 is also one okay
because that is just the sum of those two things and just back propagating
one through a plot to a sum and that's just that's just a y connection
okay now back propagating through the viterbi transformer this guy just
selected one path among two so what he's going to do is that it's
going to take those those gradients here and just copy them
on the corresponding edge on the input graph and then set the gradients for the
other path that was not selected to zero it's exactly what's happening in you
know max putting or mean pulling you're propagating through the switch at
that right position but not propagating next to it so it's nothing fancy okay
um pass it actually is the same it's uh it's just a system that selects the path
that could uh produce the correct answer and so um
i'm i'm just gonna set you know whatever uh you know through this i'm
gonna propagate the plus one to the the arcs
uh that appear here so this arc is that one
you see a zero here but i'm coming back to this in a minute
it should be a one for now and plus one here and that corresponds
to this plus one here okay and then you can propagate those
gradients all the way to the neural net and adjust the weights
so that this energy goes down okay so that will take care of making the energy
of the correct answer small okay by back propagating through this
thing now what's important about this is that
this structure here is dynamic in the sense that
if i give you a new input the number of instances of this neural net will change
with the number of segments the graph here will change uh
those graphs will change completely and so i need to be able to back propagate
through this kind of dynamical structure if you want
and this is you know situations where things like pie torch are really
important because you want to be able to handle those you know kind of
dynamical structures that change with every sample
okay so this back propagation phase takes care of
uh making the energy of the correct answer small
now how do we make the energy of incorrect answers large
well uh there's gonna be a second phase where we're just gonna in this case
we're just gonna let the system pick whatever answer it wants
okay um and um this is kind of a simplified form of
uh discriminative training for structural prediction
uh that used uses a form of perceptron loss if you want
um okay so i'm the first few stages are exactly identical to what i talked about
earlier uh but here the viterbi transformer just
picks the best pass among all the paths you don't constrain it to pick the
the uh the correct one you just literally pick whatever it wants
okay so it's going to pick the best path that it thinks that that has the lowest
energy that it thinks is the you know gives the correct answer now
the energy you get out of this necessarily is going to be smaller or
equal to the one you got previously because this one is the smallest of all
the possible configurations the other ones is not the smallest of all possible
ones it's only the smallest of the correct ones
and so this guy necessarily is going to get smaller
so we don't pick the one sorry i i lost you do we pick the one do we take out
the one that are actually producing the correct sequence or not
okay so you have two forms of it uh the form i'm explaining here you're not
taking out the correct one okay in fact in this particular example
it wouldn't make any difference but uh if you want the system to work
properly what you what you should do here
is have a pass selector that takes out the correct answers
yeah yeah exactly yes yes yes that's right so
you would want to tell the system give me your best shot
a wrong answer okay the lowest energy wrong answer exactly the white bar in
your paper right that would be the white bar
yeah here i'm not doing this i'm just asking you what's your best shot you
know i don't care if it's correct or incorrect all right
uh we'll come back to this in a minute i'm
putting this all together my loss function is going to be the difference
between the energy i get for the correct answer
minus the energy i get for whatever answer the system wants to
produce okay so i compute the difference between
those two and that's my loss function now i can back propagate through this
entire thing i told you i was back propagating just to make the energy here
small i'm not actually doing this i'm
computing a loss function here which in this case is just the difference between
this and that and uh and i'm back propagating gradient
through this entire structure right so whatever path
appears only on the left we'll get a plus one so this guy gets a
plus one because this edge only appears on this side
and so it gets a plus one the paths that only appear
on the right side like this guy sorry like this guy
get a minus one okay the gradient here gets a minus one because
uh you have a minus sign here so the gradients you know when they back
propagate they end up being minus ones okay this guy also gets minus one this
guy here appear appears on both sides and so the minus
one and the plus one cancel and these guys you know get zero
gradient it's it's in the correct path but it's also in the past that the
system produces so you shouldn't change anything
it's it's okay right so the guys that have a minus one are the incorrect paths
the other parts are in the incorrect answer but not in the correct answer
the one that i have a plus one are the the edges that are in the correct
uh answer but not in the incorrect one okay the one has zero are in neither or
they are in both right so now you get gradients here you
those gradients are gradients for all the outputs of all those neural nets you
back propagate to the neural nets and compute and update the weights okay
and what if you do this then the system will eventually minimize its loss
function which is the difference between the
energy of the correct answer and the energy of
the best answer whatever it is that loss function is the perceptron loss
and we talked about this before um in fact let me go to this just now
okay right so the the loss function we just talked about is the second
oops the second one in this list here uh this is the energy of the correct
answer minus the energy of whatever answer your
your system wants to produce okay that's the perceptron loss or the
generalized perceptron loss if you want and the bad news about this cross
function is that it doesn't have a margin so it doesn't ensure that the
energy of the incorrect answers is larger strictly
larger than the energy of the good answer uh you know it might just
collapse it might just uh make every energy zero or the same
okay so it's not a good loss function to use
it just happens to work when your energy is linearly parametrizing w
but in the general case it doesn't work so you're much better off using
something like this a hinge but in the case of a hinge what you need
to have here is this y bar which is the energy of the
most offending incorrect answer so basically uh in the second phase
as uh alfredo was uh pointing out instead of picking the path with the
lowest energy the answer with the lowest energy
you constrain the system to pick a wrong answer and then among all of those pick
the one with the lowest energy and then you take the difference between
those two energies so energy or correct answer
energy of most offending incorrect answer compute the difference between
them and uh plug this into a hinge so that
you want this energy to be lower than that energy
by at least m okay uh
and this is the kind of objective here that
uh on botu used um so it's you know it looks very similar
um uh this is uh someone something called
nce that people in um speech recognition produce so it's
basically like this looks a bit like a sigmoid
so basically it's a sigmoid function you take the difference between the energy
of the correct cancer and the energy of incorrect answers and
you plug them into a sigmoid right it's one over one plus
exponential minus blah blah and so it basically wants to make that
difference uh you know kind of small but then it
doesn't care if it's if it's too small and if it's too large it kind of gives
up and then you have you know this is the
negative likelihood loss so make the energy of the correct answer
small and then make make the log of the sum over all answers
of e to the minus the energy of those answers large
okay make the minus log large which means make the logs small
which means makes those energies large okay
and then the yoyo rabiner thing i was telling you about is
another form of objective function that sort of you know pushes them and push up
most of those are derived from sort of privacy principles but many of them
aren't okay all the ones at the top aren't
hey professor i had a question about the margin of the losses
um i think in the previous lecture we discussed how the negative
likelihood loss converges to the perceptron loss when beta is
uh going towards infinity correct or something like that but
how come the not the no loss has a positive
margin and the perceptual loss doesn't well just you know because the uh
because the the temperature is i mean the the one over beta
because beta is not is not infinite because one over beta is not zero
so yeah i mean if you take the limit of this for beta goes to infinity
uh this one over beta log sum converges to min over y
of uh energy of w i x i and so that's exactly what the
perceptron does okay so the perceptron is a
zero temperature limit or infinite beta limit of
negative likelihood indeed but the margin is essentially infinite
in this case whereas the margin here is zero
okay so there's a bit of a discontinuity here
uh admittedly though if you make beta very large here numerically
uh the energies of anything but the lowest energy
term uh i mean the the the role of the importance of the terms
uh for various y's in this sum will kind of
diminish and so numerically it may actually
uh start behaving very much like the perceptron
early on um there's a problem with it also which i
mentioned before which is that uh this uh this wants to make the energy
of incorrect answers infinite and you know it's not going to make them
infinite because as they get larger and larger they're
uh you know the the gradient of this sum with respect to each of them gets very
small but they're going to get pushed to infinity
and so it's it's not necessarily a good thing
the hinge is better in a way because you know
it just says well i just want it to be larger
you know by by some value i don't care how much
um i give you another form of the the hinge loss in the past
uh where you have a a sum over y so instead of just taking the
most of any incorrect answer in the hinge
uh you take all answers and you sum over all of them and for each of them you
have a different margin which depends on the on the
y i and the y i bar that's a more general form it might be
more expensive depending on how you compute it
there are a bunch of questions here yeah so first
there are a few students asking about the segmenter do we learn the segmenter
is he also do we backprop there is a latent variable something
uh in this particular case no it's just uh it's just um
and handcrafted heuristics uh but you could imagine
uh building a differentiable segmenter and then back propagating all the way
through it yes this was actually one of the original
plans when we built this thing in the mid-90s we never got to it
but and the reason we never got to it is because there is another approach to
character recognition which is the kind of sliding window approach which i
explained right so you just take the input you never
segment it you just apply the neural net to every location on the input and you
record the output and then you do structure prediction on top of that
so now you have to have some sort of sequence models that tells you
uh you know if i observe uh you know three three three blank blank
two four four four four it's actually three
four the blank and the two basically are spurious
right so you would have uh a grammar uh that would indicate like what are you
know correct combinations of characters on
the output and you would do this to finding the
shortest paths in the graph so the graph on the bottom is generated
by the segmenter is it correct yeah the one
with the one hop like two hops or two hops one up one hop
yep okay and there you go yeah you can think of this as kind of a simple form
of graph neural net or or kind of a specific form of graph
neural nets where uh the this entire deep learning
architecture manipulates graphs instead of tensors as its kind of
way of representing inputs okay or states
so think of this as a multi-layer architecture where the states or graphs
are annotated graphs all right and then you can have modules
here that turns graph into other graphs we used to call these graph transformers
in fact that's this is called graph transformer network right
okay so this is from 1997 right this is not recent
and uh in fact 1996. the first paper is in 1997.
uh and uh uh and then those can be you know as long as the way you compute
those scores uh is with differentiable functions that
are parametrized you can back propagate gradient through this entire thing
and i can demonstrate it how you do this in this particular case
i see then there is another question which i'm i may not be able to
understand which is what are the dimensions of of
the interpretation graphs i don't know what dimensions uh uh
dimensions so basically each uh arc okay you can do it in two ways
the way i've represented it here is that each arc has a label
uh three here for this particular edge and an energy 3.4
and then the number in parenthesis is the gradient that comes from the top
okay so here is a scalar but here on the graph at the bottom the
annotation is an entire tensor it's an image okay
so i don't specify what uh what you can annotate the graphs with as long as
whatever it is that you annotate it with if it's computed by some continuous
functions you you want to be able to propagate gradient to it
now another way of representing this graph is not by having
a separate arc here for each category but by having a vector
and the vector just contains the list of categories together with a
list of scores okay so 0 to 9 and then the list of
energies for each of the thing and that would be
just one arc but it would be annotated by
this vector yeah i see i think okay okay but because uh you know this guy the
viterbi and the past elector selects individual paths it's clearer if you
kind of write it this way how you implement it is up to you um
so those guys transform networks um there are speech recognition systems
today that uh so basically in a speech
recognition system this whole way of inferring the correct
sequence uh using for example a language model is
called a decoder okay so a decoder at the output of a
neural net generally you have a sequence of
vectors that indicate the the score the energy the probability whatever you want
of individual sounds or phonemes or sometimes words
and then you have to pass this to a language model that tells you you know
this sequence is possible that all the sequence isn't
and then it picks out the best possible interpretation according to the
language model and according to the scores produced by your system
that's called a decoder okay and the big question is
how do you back proper get rid into the decoder is only
a very small number of speech recognition systems today that actually
do this uh the latest one i think is by ronald
corbeau the original author of torch
and here's how this works uh so let's say you want to
so this is a a particular concept called graph composition or
graph transducers and which kind of explains how you can
combine graphs with each other for example
together with a language model okay so you can think of a language model
as as a graph you can represent it as a graph as a neural net it doesn't matter
but i'm going to represent i'm going to
represent it as a graph right so here this is basically a lexicon that is
represented represented as a tree tree t-r-i-e okay and it can represent
the words barn but
cute cure cap cat and card okay
so each terminal node is a word and each path
and each terminal node corresponds to a path and each path is is a word
basically right the sequence of symbols is a word
now so let's imagine our entire lexicon is is this
and we have a neural net or something that produces uh a trellis of possible
interpretation that corresponds to this graph so it says
the first character i can't tell you exactly what it is but i think it's c
with energy point four it's always energy one
or is d with energy one point eight okay it's a character recognizer
and the second one says it's x with energy point one or a with point two or
u with point eight and the last one p with point two t with point eight so
we need to do now is what is the best uh
interpretation uh of this the best path in this that also happens to be present
in our lexicon okay and the operation you need to do for this
is a concept that was invented by fernando pereira who is head of the nlp
research group and more than that actually at google research but that was
back when he was at at their labs in the early 90s
and it was sort of implemented in an open source library called the fsm
library which was implemented by mary amore who is a professor at nyu
he did this while he was at a t and then at google
and the the way you do this is this composition operation so you you start
from the initial node of both of those graphs
and you say is there a path is there a path i can
take in this graph that is legal here okay so here
i can have b or c and here i can have c o or d only c is common between the two
okay so i'm going to combine those two by saying in my output graph
i'm gonna have one of those transitions which is the the only transition that is
common here and here okay so now i'm in this node oops sorry i mean this
node here i mean that node there here i can i can take x a or u
and here i can take u or a okay so i have two possibilities u or a
a with point two u with point eight and so i add those two here
okay so basically what i'm doing here is uh whenever
i come at a node and i have to take a transition i find you know which of the
nodes that can be in here i look at the possible transitions and
if the transition exists if there is one that matches
i create a outgoing uh i going arc and i annotated by the energy of
whatever arc i had here if i also had an energy in this arc i
could just add those two terms or combine them in some way
okay so now i have two nodes here um and uh
the last one can be p or t so i can start from those two nodes and have
either p or t and it can be in either in this node or
this node so i can go here with t i can go here with p or here is t and i
end up with this those three things so now i have my
interpretation is either cat or cap or cut these are the three
interpretations that are grammatically correct and at the same
time are present as a possibility produced by neural net and now i just
have to find the shortest path there and that's my answer okay
so that operation here is called graph composition
and it basically allows you to basically combine two graphs
essentially or combine two knowledge bases that are
conceptually graphed but they could be represented by neural nets so here i can
represent this thing this whole language model by neural net uh
when i'm at a particular location it means you know when i'm here it means i
observed the sequence cu and then i can run cu in
my in my language model and ask my neural net to predict so what's the next
letter and my neural net would say well it's
either t or r uh you know in this soft max output with
the 26 letters it's going to tell me you know t and r
have five probabilities the other ones are low probabilities
or if it produces energy is going to say t and r have low energies
the other ones have higher energies okay so it doesn't matter how you
actually represent this if it's represented as a neural net then
uh implicitly then you can train this neural net you can train the language
model because you can back properly a gradient
to this entire thing okay that so that would be sort of an example
of what people called uh differentiable programming i mean
basically the way to implement this is a really really complicated program
what you need to do is backdrop a gradient through this entire program and
this program has loops and ifs and recursions okay so not trivial
i'm not telling you how we actually implemented this in 1994
1995 but but that's basically how our check reading system back in those
days was uh was implemented so the last function we used uh in the
end to train the system was actually the negative
likelihood loss function so negative likelihood says
you have an interpretation graph here where each path is a possible
interpretation and the sum of the energies along the
path is the energy of that interpretation
you give it the correct answer you select the path that have the correct
interpretation okay same on the other side so here you
combine with the grammar so the grammar restricts the
number the the the sequences to those that are syntactically correct
okay so if it's an amount on the check for example you know it's got
a decimal dot uh it might have you know a dollar sign in front it might have
stars you know um there's a grammar for it um which you
can build by hand it's a finite state grammar uh you com
you compose those two graphs and you get the set of paths in this graph that
actually contain a grammatically correct
interpretation and now you don't do viterbi you do forward okay what is
forward so viterbi computes the path
in a graph that has the minimum energy basically it minimizes with respect to
the latent variable where the latent variable is a path in the graph
forward computes the log of the sum of the exponentials of minus the energies
of all the paths okay so basically it marginalizes over the
latent variable which is the path in the graph
now it turns out that you can do this very easily and
it's very cheap it doesn't cost more than doing viterbi
uh and uh and you can back properly get to it
um and i don't have a slide for this so i'm gonna
switch to drawing it okay so
all right so you have one pass you have
another path and maybe another path that skips over here
okay and each of those guys has an energy right e1 e2
e3 e4 e5 e6 let's say okay
so if you do viterbi shortest paths in a graph you're just going to find the path
that has the minimum energy but what i'm going to talk about here is
computing so think of the path as a latent
variable z and remember to compute f of x y
you can do two things you can do mean over z of e
of x y z and remember z is the path or if you want to marginalize
you do minus 1 over beta log sum over all z's
of e to the minus beta e of x y z and that's marginalizing it's a discrete
sum of z is a discrete variable which is the case here because it's a discrete
path okay so this is f beta
x y and you can think of this as f infinity right this is the limit for
beta goes to infinity of the one at the bottom
or neural network to be trained in the model
i didn't understand the question i'm sorry can you repeat uh it's the
energy function here some simple some simple function like loss function
or some some some some neural networks to be trained in the model
it doesn't matter okay this is the this is the energy that you use to measure
the score of an answer y okay the observation
is x yeah the answer you are supposed to predict in this case a
sequence of symbols uh is y um and so for you know each of those
things here is annotated with a particular y
okay so this could be uh you know uh
you know each of those arcs is annotated by a symbol
so let's say a and this is b and this is b
and c and this is i don't know x and this is g or something right
so here the possible interpretation for y so y would be a string of symbols and
it can be either a b or it can be
b c g or it can be c cg okay this is c
okay those are the next x right ec sorry i'm sorry you're right this is
this is a six it's x thanks you're right sorry about that
okay those are the only three possible interpretations
uh in that in that graph that can come out of that graph
um and z is which fast you're taking okay so
if z is the first path then the output will be a b if z is the second part the
output will be bcg et cetera okay okay thank you
right but this is not used for training this is the energy function okay use for
inference um okay so
this the the log of the sum of the exponentials of the energies
uh for all the paths the sum of uh over all the paths okay
so the sum here is over path okay uh that's like marginalizing over z
and we saw that before right we explained that before
um now how do i compute this um now it turns out it's very simple
it's done using what's called a forward algorithm i'm actually going to draw a
different tree a different graph a graph that's
going to look more like the one i had before
which was kind of like this right okay so y is a sequence of uh
three symbols in this case and uh each um
and the first symbol can be um oh i'm sorry i'm using nodes here
instead of instead of arcs that's a little confusing
let me correct that okay so each path in this graph is a
possible interpretation okay so for each each edge i'm taking
i'm emitting a symbol and i don't have skipping connections so
here they all have exactly four symbols coming out
because every path is of length four okay
but how do i compute this sum this this sum
uh basically i go at a node okay when i'm at i don't know it here let's let's
take this node right right here i'm gonna call it red
okay the the cost from the input node
the the energy from the input node to that node is the log of the sum of
the exponentials of the energies from along all paths to go from the input
node to that node okay so
and of course you know i have i have an energy right here which is just the
energy of that branch i have an energy here which is just the
energy of that branch okay i have an f here um
and to compute the uh the f for this guy i just compute the
log of the sum of the exponentials of those two guys
okay right so let me unwrap this okay i've got an energy here
y1 i've got energy here y2 i got one here y3 oh e3 sorry and one
here uh this guy is e4
all right the f i'm gonna get here okay so this is i'm going to call this
i'm going to call it anything so the value i should have here
is is e1 plus
e3 exponential of that minus beta that
plus exponential minus beta e2 plus e4
and i take minus one over beta log of this
okay so how is the event calculated i mean
the smaller yield lower list whatever comes out of your
energy right um each of those graphs you know as i said
you you represent uh possible interpretations as a graph each
node in the graph has an energy and a complete energy of the function
which is an f of x y for a particular y in a particular z following a path is uh
is is uh is e of x y z and now what you want to compute is log
of sum of e to the minus e of x y z uh which is the
marginalization over all the paths so it's basically combining the cost of
all the paths in kind of a soft minimum way right
but the algorithm is is super simple because
uh you maintain a variable basically for each node
for each node you compute a variable alpha
for a particular node and it's going to be equal to
minus log sum over all the nodes that are
up from from so let's say it's not i up from i
okay so all the parent nodes of of i and then you do e to the minus beta the
alpha uh k and and you add to it
uh e of uh
k i which would be the energy of the link coming from node k
to node i okay that's called a forward algorithm
and if you've heard about this it's actually a special case
of the so-called belief propagation algorithm
so belief propagation is a general algorithm for
graphical models and [Music]
the fourth algorithm is a special case when the your graph is basically a chain
graph okay um but i'm not going to go into
this you can take a course on video nets or
or graphical models or probabilistic methods you take a
course you know with rajesh she will explain that to you
this would take us too far but that that would be
kind of the thing okay so now this is just a feed forward neural net
where basically where the function at each
node is a log of sum of exponentials plus
addition of some some term right this is a neural
net where alpha i is the activation and of
of the the neurons if you want the nodes and the weights are those uh
e of ki that link unit k to unit i okay and the operations you do is log
some exponentials so instead of a neural net in which you do
a product by a weight and then you sum the products
here you add the weights and then you do a log sum exponential
algebraically it's actually equivalent this is like
weighted sum in the log domain okay but the point is you can do this
forward prop this forward algorithm and you can back propagate gradient so
whatever f you get at the end you know by the time you run through this network
at the end here you basically get f of x y the value at that node the alpha
here is f of x y and
you've eliminated z by doing this log of sum of exponentials over all paths
right now if you want to compute the the gradient
of f of x y with respect to each of the e k i
which themselves probably are outputs of some neural net you can do that you can
back propagate to this network okay it's a it's a neural net who's
again whose structure is dynamic it you know it changes from
example to example but you can you can clearly
backpropagate gradient to it and that's basically what what we do
here in this system we we run the forward
algorithm on this graph and we get a score which is the
log of the sum of the exponentials of minus the energies for all the paths
okay we do the same here we get another score
i mean it's minus log of the sum of the exponential of the energy of minus
energy okay this guy necessarily is larger than this
one you compute the difference and that's the negative likelihood loss
it's a difference between the log sum x of energy over the
relative variable of the correct answer and looks a mass over a latent variable
of every answer although here these are grammatical
answers but it's the same and then you just back propagate
gradients through this entire thing and then it goes back properly
propagating gradient through this uh graph here which you can think of as
some sort of weird neural net with where the node operation is like some
exponentials and you get gradients for each of the
e's and each of the e's are the values that you get here which
are produced by the neural net and so you get you get
gradients with respect to the parameters when you're on it
okay so that's structural prediction for you
there's a couple more topics i wanted to talk about today and variational
methods in bayesian inference because we talked about it in the context of ea
but without really explaining what it was or at least i didn't maybe you did
alfredo but like the general form of variational inference or i can talk
about the lagrangian formulation of backprop i can actually do both because
it's kind of fast it will take more than five minutes but you can leave whenever
you want okay then let's go for both uh the long
orange thing is short so i'm going to do that first okay
okay so you can formulate back prop as a minimization under constraint
so you have an input variable x is going through
a first functional module let's call it f1
of x w1 and it produces
uh we're gonna call it z1 actually let me call this f0 f0
okay and then the second one is going to be f1
of z1 w1 and that produces z2
etc so and then at the end we have the last module and it goes into
some sort of uh energy term
okay with let's say desired output if we do supervise running but it doesn't
matter it's just a cost let's call this guy z
n okay zn and y
um okay so the the forward pass can be written as
z k plus 1 is equal to f
k of ck wk
okay that's just a forward pass and then you have a cost function
c which you want to minimize which is z of
c of zn y okay that's just whatever cost
function you want to minimize now you can write that you can write the
the entire problem as a minimization of the
constraint so and the and the statement is minimize
c with the constraint such that
the above constraint is verified okay and
when you have a minimization problem under constraint the best thing to do is
to write a lagrangian right so you write a lagrange function i'm not going to
tell you right away what is this function of
and for a single training sample x y is going to be the
the cost zn y okay
well the other thing we might we might say also is there is another constraint
which is that z zero equals x
plus sum over layers okay so we're going to have an index k
from 1 to n and a lagrange
multiplier and a constraint which should be
equal to 0 and that constraint is going to be
zk plus 1 minus fk of uh z k
w k and i need to i'm gonna call this lambda k plus one
and this is gonna have to be up to n minus one and probably starting
at zero actually
okay so this is a lagrangian formulation of
uh my back part problem where basically you have an overall cost function
and i have a bunch of constraints so the constraints are that
the input to layer k is the output of layer k minus one
okay so this regression is a function of x
y all the lambdas the lambda k's all the z's and w
all the w's okay so what i need to do now to do this uh
minimization under constraint is i need to
do dl over d lambda k equals zero okay and if i this condition
uh the the gradient of l with respect to
lambda k is just the it's just this
right i mean the k plus one i'm sorry it's just this parenthesis okay so i
just get zk plus 1 equal
fk of zk wk which is just the forward propagation formula
if i do dl over d z k equals zero
uh it's a little more complicated right so i get the first term
which is lambda k because i'm going to have a z k here and that z
k is going to be a factor of this lambda lambda k here right so i
get uh i get i i guess i get longer k transpose
and then i get minus and then for this zk
i have a lambda k plus one here times the jacobian function of this
with respect to z okay so it's going to be
something like dfk of zkw over zk
that's it times ooh okay
times lambda k plus one transpose and that should be equal to zero so i'm
going to rearrange all that stuff and what i get
is uh lambda k equals
dfk zkw with respect to zk so that the
jacobian matrix uh of f transposed times lambda k plus 1.
and funnily enough this is actually the backpropagation formula
right this is the thing that gives you the gradients at la at
level k given the gradients of level k plus one you multiply by the jacobian of
of the of the box that you propagate it through
okay so you don't have to think about it you know you just kind of
write back prop as a constraint optimization problem and backprop
naturally comes out of it now the first people to figure this out
were people in control theory in fact first people to figure this out
where people like lagrange or or or euler or people like hamilton and
jacoby that's the classical formulation of of
of mechanics if you want um and in mechanics when you write uh
something like this you say uh where c of zn
uh y would be uh uh the energy of the system
like a potential energy is something like this and then the other term was
basically implements the dynamic constraints the fact that
you have a differential equation that tells you that the state at time t plus
one is a function of the state at time t
with some constraint right so that's the dynamic constraint and
then if you do this uh you you know you figure out that
uh the if you have an energy for every you know
think of k now as a time step and the forward propagation as
a differential equation that governs a system
and then you could have a term here that is not just
an energy term at the output but basically an energy term that
uh you can have one of those terms for
every time step right so the lagonchan function would be summer time
steps of c for that time step of
z k okay and there might be some external variable
uh let's call it y k you know plus those constraints
k plus one minus f k of z k w k
okay and the the sun takes place over all things
um when you look at uh you know lagoon formulation of classical mechanics
that's basically the way they're expressed
c is the energy and the second term are the constraints now in classical
mechanics uh the the lambda variable is actually
the momentum so z is the position variables and
lambda becomes the momentum so the second term becomes basically the
the kinetic energy or the negative kinetic energy more more
specifically um anyway this is just an apartheid okay
why am i telling you this it's because conceptually
the you know the mathematics of this is super simple if you know
lagrangian minimization of the constraint
and this is something you can use also in
a new class of model called neural ode so neural
ordinary differential equation and this is something else wanted me to talk
about thank you
so neural od so this is a type of neural net which is basically a recurrent
neural net where you say my state at time t plus delta t
is equal to my state at time t plus delta t times you know some function
uh which is a constant function of uh zt
and a bunch of parameters which are fixed okay they're not they don't value
with time i can write it this way i can write it in a
differential equation form where i can say dz
over dt at time t is equal to f of zt
w okay so that's the differential equation ordinary differential equation
uh in this case the first order well it depends what's in z
but um if i you know i could i could i can express
just about anything this way uh and the question is how do you train
something like this and basically uh if you write the lagrangian
formulation of this it's trivial the uh so there are two ways
you might want to train something like this you might want to train the system
to map one point you know z at time zero
to a particular point zero times big t after some trajectory you may not want
to constrain the trajectory you just just want it to reach that point and you
don't care what it does afterwards i just wanted to reach that point and so
you can have a cost function which is basically
you know the distance of z to that target point
uh zero big t you know i'm gonna call it y
and then so the target would be uh the target would be a point y
and then your cost function would be the distance between
z t and y or something like that okay another thing you might want to do is
you might want to train the system so that
it has stable states at particular points y
okay so that uh for a particular point y that you decide from your training set
uh f of this particular y w equals zero
which means you know that state is going to be stable
right the the trajectory so you would have a point
y in your space and then you know you might start from some point
when you arrive at that point the the dynamics stop stops
so if you formulate this in terms of uh lagoon it becomes like super simple in
the sense that the gradients now contrary to backpop through time so
if you were to unfold this network here consider this a recurrent net
and you enfold it in time to compute the gradient
of the end point with respect to the parameters
you you cannot have to and with respect to the initial for you have to back
propagate through time right you have to kind of
remember the entire sequence and then do backdrop two time
okay but if what you're interested in is just learning a stable state like this
then you don't need to store the trajectory you
uh you start from some point you convert to
some other point and you want to make y a stable state
what you just need to do is ensure that this is true uh
and the way you can do this is uh you know basically by minimizing your
cost which would be some something like the norm the square norm
of f of y w but the point of the the point is that
you don't need to remember the entire trajectory
the gradient with respect to the weights can be obtained by
running a very similar type of differential equation backwards in time
and i'm sorry i'm not going to be able to go into details of that i can refer
you to a paper um so this is a neural ide paper which
doesn't really mention that but there is an earlier paper of mine called a
theoretical framework
for back propagation and basically it explains this
uh lagrangian formulation as well as how you apply it
for recurrent nets uh that might be sort of
you know continuous and continuous in time and that you want to train to
go to particular fixed points uh this is paper from 1988.
it's not recent uh you'll find it on my web page
down on the bottom of the publication page but i don't want to go into the
details of this and there is the bayesian stuff asian
stuff yes people are still here i don't know
they are enjoying it stick around you don't have to if you don't want to
uh it's not the basic stuff it's more the virtual
oh sorry yeah you're right i'm not confused
uh so let's say i have some uh loss
function okay and i'm going to talk about a loss
not not an energy but it's the same thing
and my last function uh is a marginalized loss function over a
latent variable right so remember you know i i talked about
this before if you have an energy function
f of x y let's say and you want to derive it from a more
elementary energy function e of x y z by doing the equivalent operation of
marginalizing over z's yeah so the way you uh you
marginalize right is you uh you do
minus beta e to the minus you sum over all z's and you take minus one over beta
log okay so this is uh the formula for
marginalizing a relative variable um and that also applies to
loss functions you know whatever function you want to marginalize over a
latent variable that's what you compute so let's say you
have a model with a latent variable and
you don't know what the value of the latent variable is and you want to
compute what is my loss uh which would be the log of the sum of
the exponentials of the loss over all values of the latent variables so
right so i'm kind of marginalizing over this certain variable let's say it's a
you know rational autoencoder or something i have a latent variable in
the middle and i want to compute the
minus 1 over beta log sum over all values of my little variable of e to the
minus beta l i'm using l but i could use just any
symbol here this is whatever function you need to compute
but it's useful for things you want to minimize like energies or
or or objectives okay so here this loss function here is
no longer a function of z it's only a function of x and y
i can rewrite this as the following
q of z e to the minus beta l of x y z
or eq right i've just multiplied and divided by q of z
okay i've done nothing now q of z here uh i assume is a
a probability distribution over z so it's a
density function that integrates to 1 when i integrate over z
so you can interpret this integral as the expected value
with respect to the distribution of e to the minus beta l of x y z divided
by q of z okay now
here's the trick there's something called jensen's inequality
and jensen's inequality says something very interesting it says
let's imagine i have a convex function like say minus log okay i'm not drawing
minus log here very well but it looks a bit like minus log now
if i uh if i take um a bunch of values
over a range okay and i compute the average of the value
of the function minus log over that range
okay because the function is convex i'm going to get a value that is smaller
than the function applied to the average okay so my diagram is not that great
because the the curvature is not high enough let me
draw it again so here's a convex function i'm going to
vary a variable here over a range okay and compute the average of that
function over that range so it's going to you
know give me some some value
you know probably around here and then i'm going to take the
average of all those values in this range the average of the range the
midpoint of that range and pass it to the to the function
okay and i get i get something below this so
i didn't draw this properly so if i take the average of this plus
this you know this this this this and this
i'm going to get something that's higher than that because
because the function is not convex if the is convex if the function was
straight then the average after going to the
function would be the same as before going to the function right if
i computed the average of all those values
or the y values of those points it would be at the same place
as the function applied to the average okay so you can make the intercept
between the the convex function in a line right that goes from those two
extrema that's right yeah there you go so that
that the mean would be the yeah that point yeah that's right
so the the the the mean applied to the function values
would be something like this chord it wouldn't be that but it would be kind of
close to that okay now it let's forget about a function like
actually i should have explained this inverse simple way which is just two
values um let's say it's just the sum of two
terms okay so i have a convex function i have
two values uh the average of those two values after
i passed through the function okay so basically let's say this is
my function is minus log so the average of minus log of let's
call it x1 and x2 minus log of x1 plus minus log of x2
divided by 2 okay is this point
okay and then minus log of x1 plus
x2 divided by 2 is that point and that's below
okay and jensen's inequality basically says if you have a convex function
like like minus log um the
okay and then here i computed on average but you know it's true for any
expectation it says the
expectation so basically
convex of expectation over any distribution of some function h
well that would be z in that case okay uh
i have to write this in the proper way is less than or equal
to sum over z q z of this convex function
applied to h and z okay that's john's sense inequality
so this this works with uh minus log which means i can write that
my objective function here is less than uh minus one over beta which i'm going
to actually put inside uh i take this back
it's going to be less than sum over z of q of z
times minus 1 over beta log e to the minus beta l of x y z
divided by q z okay obviously the
[Music] the one over beta the minus one over
beta log exponential minus beta cancel okay so what i get is
sum summary z q of z l of x y z
so that's just the expected value of l averaged over the distribution q z and
then i get a second term and the second term is the negative
log 1 over beta the negative log of of q of z but there is you know q of z
is a denominator so i'm going to bring it to the top
that's going to cancel the minus 1 over beta and so i'm going to get something
like plus 1 over beta
log q of z right and i can write this again as sum over z
of q of z l x y z
plus sum over z 1 over beta q z plug q z
okay this is the
average loss energy whatever it is let's call it
energy and this is the
uh this is one over this is minus one over beta times the
entropy of q
okay the entropy of a distribution is minus
sum over the random variable of distribution log distribution okay so
this is minus one over beta e entropy so what does that mean what
that means is that i have an upper bound on my the last
function that i want to minimize l of x y okay for my energy that i want
to minimize whatever it is whatever function it is i want to
minimize i have an upper bound on it now and this upper bound is the sum of two
terms one is the average of the energy i get
by basically sampling the latent variable
okay so i have a system with a latent variable i sample some
value of the latent variable according to some distribution q
which of course i pick a queue from which i can easily sample
okay i can choose q whatever i want whatever i want right
um so i pick a queue gaussian whatever and i i pick a z according to that
distribution and i compute the expected value of the function i want to
minimize with respect to uh to that q and i can do this by just
sampling z from the the q distribution and then
computing the average of the function l that i obtain as a result
okay so that's the first term and then the second term
is the entropy of z so what i need to do is
basically change my distribution z in such a way that
the entropy is maximized so if it's a gaussian for example it means i need to
make the variance of z as large as possible but if i make
it too large then the average energy term is going to blow up
so i need to optimize this overall this this
this whole function and if i optimize this whole function
with respect to q and with respect to whatever parameter of l i want to
minimize because l is an objective function with
respect to i don't know weights of a neural net or something right
so i can simultaneously minimize with respect to
those parameters w which i didn't write here and with respect to the q
uh distribution and if the q distribution is in a family that's wide
enough uh then this upper bound will be fairly
close to the actual loss that i want to minimize which is
the marginalized loss over the over the latent variable but i never
need to actually compute explicitly the marginalization of a latent variable so
this is a way of marginalizing a related variable
without actually doing it okay by marginalizing over a latent variable
that you can sample from like a gaussian but
what you have to do is maximize its entropy
and when you think about variational autoencoders that's just what they do
okay they minimize the expected reconstruction error which is l of x y z
with respect to the parameters by sampling the latent variable z
according to a gaussian distribution okay but at the same time there is
what's called the kl term which is the second term but basically tries to make
that distribution as high entropy as possible now this
formula is exactly identical to a formula that
people use in uh in statistical physics so physicists
have a very famous formula
which is this it says the free energy is equal to the average
energy minus the temperature times the entropy
okay what they call the temperature is what i call one over beta
okay and that's identical to this formula because here this is the minus
entropy okay this is the same formula so what
we're minimizing now is a is a free energy and if q of z
is sufficiently powerful to actually be the
actual distribution that it needs to be then the inequality becomes an equality
but um but that's the idea of variational
uh methods you basically use gensense inequality to turn
the log of a of a of an average into the average of the log okay and now
you get an upper bound right so it's uh
this step right here when i turn the equality
uh that was here into an inequality by applying json's inequality
what i did is that i put the log inside there was a log
outside and i put it inside so now it's the expectation of a log instead of a
log of an expectation okay and then
because this is a ratio it's a difference of two logs and
because this is uh exponential of an energy and i take the log and i divide
by beta i get this kind of nice formula and now
this is called a variational free energy okay and you get the expected value of
the energy minus the inverse temperature times the
entropy of the distribution now how you minimize this you know is
another story but what that means now is that you can use
a surrogate distribution to sample from your
to sample unit and variable form you don't have to sample from the real
distribution when which uh you know here the the real distribution
of z is really complicated i should have written it
the real distribution of z p or z is e to the minus theta this actually
would be a different beta it doesn't have to be the same
e of x y z divided by the integral over z of e to
the minus beta prime of e of x y
z that's the real if you plug this p into um
into here uh the the equality here the inequality
here becomes an equality okay you can show that uh
the the smallest value for this variable is when q equals p
okay and then uh the two terms in the inequality are equal
okay so that's kind of the sort of energy view if you want of
variational inference if you need to compute the log of a sum
of exponentials replace it by uh
the average of your function plus a entropy term and
that will give you an upper bound you minimize the upper bound and because
you push down on you you push down on the upper bound you also push down on
the function you actually want to minimize
beautiful it's like you know the bare bones kind of
simplest formulation of variational inference
okay in terms of energy uh i mean you you can replace l by
p and with some normalized stuff right but it doesn't it makes it more
complicated i mean it doesn't make any difference
really but it makes it harder to interpret
okay uh i think we're done this is a lot of people stuck around for
this sort of extracurricular session of more than half an hour yeah
40 people uh it was a pleasure teaching this class
particularly given the circumstances alright see you tomorrow guys and stay
safe all right take care bye